All right. Hello, welcome everyone. I'm
going to start this stream with a GitHub
push.
All
right, it is June 8th, 2025 and this is
active inferrant stream
14.2. First, where we're going today in
terms
of AI art to quickly give a little
visual
beginning.
No, I'll just show.
Sorry about that. Was just working up to
this last moment to get this going.
Where we're headed is using RX
infer multi-agent trajectory planning
example and using GNN to give an
exact reconfiguration. So we're going to
be using
generative not generalized notation
notation to
yield this simulation in RX infer. So
there's a couple steps to go over. Uh
this is just sort of a live working
uh presentations and to be refined and
polished. I just wanted to get it all
into this one stream given all these
recent updates.
So to the stream agenda and also people
watching live I will look forward to
your comments and and
ideas. Let's start with uh looking at
the areas we'll go
into. First just some overview on the
tools I'm using cursor 1.0 which came
out recently. GNN generalized notation
notation. Check out stream 14.1 if you
want to see more using LLM via cursor
mainly claude 4 and it's going to be
about reverse and forward engineering in
the RX infer setting. Okay, where we're
headed is a robust information supply
chain from plain text configuration to
executable simulation. So here's what
that is going to look like again with
the AI art. We have GNN the plain text
GNN moving through all of these stages
the triple play graphical on through
executed simulation. So whether we think
about that as meeting in the middle
between the forward specification of GNN
and all of these different kinds of
things that we might want to do with GNN
like the type checking all the modules
of the package and the the golden spike
moment is meeting in the middle with the
reverse engineering of RX and fur
examples and the forward engineering of
the GNN package so that we can end up
with this being in the middle between
the plain text which gives us all these
benefits of plain text reproducibility
etc and all these functionalities of
GNN.
Uh in the main first section, I'll go
over what that specifically was. Talk
about the reverse engineering in the RX
infer example from script to more of a
package and then meeting that package
with a forward engineering pass from the
GNN schema and pipeline on through the
needed
configuration. And that's the golden
spike. Again, just a metaphor. Uh there
have been many changes to the GNN
package and still a few more that could
occur with the logging and so on. But
I'll go through a few sections of change
and
documentation little bit more on the
golden spike and the
analogy. Then we'll see what people
comment where that goes. And I have a
little bit of manual writing as well in
terms of thinking about what that means
from a organizational perspective and
for active inference and for the
institute and all that.
Okay. Going to the
package. All right. In the doc RX infer
folder, the first thing is this short
script clone RX infer examples. And this
clones a
repo which is a fork of the main RX
infer examples that I have on my
personal GitHub account. And this I sync
it up with the main examples repo which
is awesome that they're putting out more
and more and different. And then in the
support folder on my fork first there's
a setup Julia script to get your
environment ready. And then there's a
notebooks to scripts Julia which takes
the notebooks from the examples and it
turns them all into scripts just by
extracting out the code blocks. So they
don't all necessarily work um but on the
first pass but it gets all the
content again to this forward reverse
engineering idea. Here's the
process. So
first and the links to all this are in
the video description. First use that
notebooks to scripts
script to uh convert the notebook into a
script. Sometimes it might run away.
Other times you might need to change
certain things about the control flow.
And first step is to just lock in the
single script. So what that looks like
in the case
here in so then it clones in. This is
work I did on the fork to get this is
the the reverse engineering part with RX
infer
scripts advanced
examples multi-agent
trajectory
archive. So this is the working single
script version of the multi- aent
trajectory
model. Just for context, where this
takes us is
these four agents that do a negotiation
of avoidance collision and obstacle uh
avoidance. So different different
collision avoidance and that's happening
with at the heart of it all this app
model block as always in RX infer that
is used by the path planner inference
step. This is the
uh kind of the kernel and then RX infer
is making that kernel of the generative
model. The explicit probabilistic joint
distribution makes it look a lot more
like the math or the analytical
description of the generative model and
everything else is pushed into the
inference methods. So that's that kind
of idea of writing shorter app model
blocks that distinguish different
generative models and then everything
else is like rendering that out into the
graphical model with the stereotyped
inference
routines from that single
script take it to more of a configular
modular approach.
So that was probably several hours,
several dozen prompts, but not something
that couldn't be done eventually in an
automated fashion to split up that
single
script that which was only lightly
modified from the notebook format which
is 339 lines to modify it from single
script into in this case almost 10
different scripts.
Some of them are really short, but they
clarify and there's other ways that it
probably could have been disassembled or
or
disarticulated. Um, this separates out
different
functions and also adds a lot of
visualization and and logging methods.
Third step from that configure uh from
that multi- script
package all the hardcoded variables take
it out to a config toml
file. So this is like a little domain
specific language just for this one
example in this one case where this
gives all the configuration needed. So
instead of just having the values coded
in the scripts look to this central
config standalone
file there's multiple ways or stages of
generalizing the variables like the
dimensional state spaces initial
parameterizations constraint variables
number of agents simulation variables
like time steps into this config
block that is going from and and all
along the way uh confirming that the the
simulation is still running. So that was
the reverse engineering of RX and Fur.
So it's kind of like the original
notebook was like a handmade chair and
this was like reverse engineering it so
that we could have this cartridge which
gets run like a disassembled IKEA
factory separating out the methods.
Whereas the original example is great
and really informative in terms of a
blog post.
Readable introduces things
sequentially and shows what RX infer is
doing and gets to those exact
simulations. This shows like one path
through the flow and it's a custommade
artifact. And again that reverse
engineering process was taking it into
these different uh disassembled
components but exactly reproducing it
and then pulling out all the
configuration into a
config. Uh so that's the reverse
engineering of the RX and first side.
Now in the
forward
rendering this is going from a GNN
file to that config because if we can if
we know from that reverse engineering
phase that getting to that config is
going to allow the execution of the
simulation. Then the other side of that
meeting in the middle is getting the GNN
file into that config format.
So here is in in this examples folder a
GNN style markdown
file with all of the parameters that
need to be specified in the
config so that when you're in SRC and
you run
main is going to run all of the all of
the the steps which are turned
on of the 14 steps which are each their
own numbered script with the same name
module. Whichever ones you have
enabled which is
in the new file in pipeline module
config. You can turn whichever of these
modules on or off. That's different from
last time. And
uh that RX infer GNN example gets passed
through step one checks the files. Step
two does setups of the virtual
environment. Step three does any tests.
Step four, type checker
output. We can look in the type
checking and see for example that RX
infer even though these resource
estimates are are not currently
specifically accurate especially
compared across different packages but
the uh resources are calculated for that
RX infer example just by virtue of it
being a GNN.
Then
there's let's continue looking through
the step five exports into a bunch of
different outputs. Six makes
visualizations and then of interest here
is nine which renders what we want into
the tombble and 11 it's going to call
the LLM. So here's the exports. This is
the reexport of the GNN file and the
export of the GNN file in other formats
like XML and other graph formats. That's
step five. Step six,
visualization. we
get the matrix
visualization of all of the state spaces
and ontology
assertions of this
model. So like this is an interesting
example in this
engineering RX infer notation name space
A is often used for state transitions
whereas in the active inference textbook
B is used for state transitions but it's
an example of why we don't want to have
a welding between letters and ontology
terms. we want to have the flexibility
to use the same letters for different
ontologies and language in in different
settings. So it's perfect example of
that of just the ontology um assertion
space and all the variables can be
described just because it was GNN file.
Okay,
now we get to step nine.
Oh, it didn't run
completely. To run it
again. Python 3
main.
Um, this will run the in the
render in the render folder in SRC.
In the RX
infer section, there's a toml
generator. So, this will read in the
GNN and then output the
toml which is the one that we knew that
we wanted from the RX infer side.
Then this script in the RX infer folders
and
doc demonstrates the GNN RX infer
pipeline for multi-agent trajectory
planning. It performs two-step
validation. So first it runs a baseline
execution from the clone of the RX infer
examples.jl which doesn't use GNN.
Then
those files for the example are all
copied over into this uh folder right
here multi-agent trajectory planning and
then it's logged in the running of the
script that the config was replaced with
the one regenerated from the
GNN. So it's a clean
um functional replacement
experiment to show that the GNN
structured
file
here can be used as part of this bigger
pipeline which includes the type
checking, the category theory, all these
these different kinds of ontology
connections and
yield the target
TOML that we know will make the
simulation work for the reverse
engineered disarticulated RX
infer
example. So I hope that that has been
conveyed. It took a long time, I think,
overall to get here, but it had long
been the triple play vision that we
would have a unified plain text format
for the math diagrams and visualizations
and executable code. So, it's like,
okay, how do we get triple play
integrity? So we could have things like
okay well you change the visual
representation with a drag and drop and
then it changes the executable code.
It's
like how is that going to work formally?
Well, a lot of the examples scripts and
scientific papers use like a all-in-one
script which can make reproducing the
example simpler and more monolithic but
then give fewer degrees of freedom
because you might be just like 700 lines
in the middle of the script and it's not
clear how you change certain aspects
more structural about the
um model. So, how do we get to the
ability for there to be a triple play
where changes in one can be traced to
changes in the other? And that was where
Yakob and I were thinking maybe we have
some sort
of
intra or infra
lingua with the generative uh a
generalized notation notation.
Let's find that quote.
Um,
so RX
Infer or any other software, we could
try doing a reverse engineering of a
PIMDP
script gives the ability
to set everything
needed except the state space of the
generative
model. So there's still a lot to be
explored in terms of how do we customize
control flows and more simulation
environment scale
factors.
Um and also uh
uh a lot more to say. Um but suffice to
say that
for simple
reproducing of standalone examples, this
reverse engineering sort of forensic
phase is a very important proof of
concept.
So in active inference, research models
are often conveyed through assemblages
of natural language, pseudo code,
programming language, analytical
formulas, and pictorial representations.
In this paper, we present GNN as a
flexible and expressive language
tailored for expressing active inference
models and encomp encompassing various
relevant aspects of languages including
ontology, morphology, grammar and
pragmatics. By leveraging GNN as an
active inferral lingua or interlingua,
infringingua, superlingua,
intringingua, we aim to bridge and
respect gaps among different modeling
approaches in order to facilitate
interdisciplinary research.
So how can this be used?
Well, for our
education, we can have
these
welltempered generative model
infrastructural
pipelines and
specific, well doumented, interpretable
configurations that help us understand
and communicate and figure out what
different generative models and process
flow elements are
There's also a lot of engineering
uses.
So there could and will be many use
cases where GNN is not a front feature
of the product. It's just a useful,
increasingly
useful open source and stack for
connecting the
dots between existing examples and ways
to modify and design with those motifs.
And then increasingly forward use of
this kind of metarogramming program
synthesis type approach to generative
modeling which is going to have all
these benefits for making them easier to
design like just being able to prompt an
LLM and say make me a GNN file that
represents this like we'll do probably
later in this stream. um all the way on
through having the resource estimation.
All these features that we want for any
generative
model can be
abstracted and brought into this
infrastructure grade pipeline. So
that once there are more and more paths
and understanding about how do you get
more and more generically or in all
these different situations to executable
simulations.
um using this pipeline and putting in
the cartridge helps separate and and
give a lot of reproducibility and
expressivity to the compute that happens
in between.
So there's the reverse engineering
approach which is just taking scripts
exactly as they are and within that
language or in more of a port or
transfer doing an exact reproduction
effort and then from there maybe certain
pieces can be flipped out but it's
always good to know that we can exactly
reproduce using the same variable names
the same ontology assertions. So that
becomes kind of like a substrate of well
paper one modeled attention this way and
in natural language they described
attention this way. Paper two in a
different programming language in a
different natural language said this
about attention. And here's how we can
use ontology across the natural language
and the computational elements to talk
about where those are similar or
different. Buzzing can be used for for
different functions. So for example,
once we have the config and the ability
to separate out these different
variables, we could see like what are
the perturbations that are allowable
because we didn't change any of the
logic or the control flow. So for
example, if the number of agents were
simply changed to 50, then as it is
currently written, there might need to
be some other refactorizations of state
spaces, which just changing NR agents
wouldn't exactly do. It might just be
part of a loop and then the loop would
break because it's like, wait, there
were only four because we only had four
initial locations. So then you go okay
okay
okay how could we develop configuration
spaces where number of agents at at a
programmatic level had a relationship to
instantiations of matrices and other
features like knowing that you needed to
have as many of these blocks as you do
agents. So in this exact situation again
it was first just an exact reverse
engineering but from that reverse
engineering through insight and through
program uh synthesis and fuzzing
approaches we can explore like what
happens when the DT is 0.01 or do a
program sweep across generate
simulations where DT ranges from this to
this while the number of iterations
ranges from that to that. So then that
gives this ability to explore what are
the functional and the performance
aspects optimization and then we can go
even
further especially as the visualization
and the disco
pi
features improve. So here not every
single variable was captured by the
disco pi category theory description but
it wasn't the focus here but that would
be something that could be worked on and
again in general the goal is a wide
range of defined and checked GNN
formats ranging from discrete time
continuous time all these different
kinds of scenarios we continue to build
out that space uh and neighborhood hoods
of different models which can be
interpreted a certain way. So there's a
lot of things that could happen with the
processing pipeline like how do we know
that this PIMDP one we only want to
render into PIMDP and the RX inver so
okay should we include that information
in the file andor in the file name how
should that be handled by the different
modules those are the kinds of software
improvements that would then allow us to
when we run it right now let's just say
we had it perfectly working for
rendering PIMDP to PIMDP and RX infer to
RX infer we still might get 50% errors
and then it would try to chase around
fixing but it didn't need to be fixed.
But then if we had some examples which
are actually quite few if any where we
have the same exact analytical situation
being cross rendered into PMDP and RX
infer. So those would be some
interesting ways to check that all of
the cross rendering is working
well. Okay, returning to the agenda and
if anyone has any
uh suggestions or questions, write them.
Otherwise, I'm just going to try to get
through the rest of the agenda, go to
some of the manual writing, see if
there's some interesting thing that we
could look maybe look at the
documentation and just kind of have this
um informal bring it together of all
these recent developments over the last
couple of days so that at least it's
been worked through and put out there
for for those who want to explore it.
and then it will return in in more forms
over the coming months.
So the golden spike was meeting in the
middle between reverse engineering of
the n=1 rx infer example into the
components into the config
form pipeline execution
summary is a JSON
file. So, what's cool about this is
different steps can be tucked in with
the
arrow. So, you can look at just the
logging for each step and it probably
makes it more machine readable as well.
But like here's the full logging for the
step
five and then step six visualization and
so
on. in terms of how the pipeline overall
has
changed. Big picture is still the exact
same which is all the documentation is
in docs. The RX infer script is in there
for now just to be close to RX infer
cloned repo and all the source code is
in src. So you just delete the output
folder and then run
main.py here.
It runs
whichever of the modules are configured
to run in
config.py, it will run those
sequentially. Each of them have a a
function and this is
all very uh documented up in the repo.
Okay.
GNN computational science, deployment
science, multi-agent systems, being able
to design and describe these systems.
And it starts quietly being able to
write and read and modify GNN files in
markdown that start to flow out through
more and different places better and
better. And that's just one trace
through an information supply chain
which hops across different operating
systems and mines and servers and all of
that. However, with this GNN entry point
or meeting point, there's the ability to
do some verified computing and tracing a
little bit better from which generative
model and which data inputs and so on
are run how,
when to yield what
outputs. And that flow from abstract
concept to concrete execution is unified
slashunifiable.
um some of the most
uh important ways that people could
explore from here getting the GNN repo
examples working on their own
machine making GitHub issues or comments
with ways to improve it.
um seeing what kinds of
scenarios
and value propositions they'd like to do
themselves. Uh in which case just go for
it and report back, measure back or to
to partner or support the institute so
that we can have these kinds of tools
being developed very functionally here.
Okay, here's a little bit of a
interlude, manual, manually written
interlude to contrast with the large
amount of computerenerated material.
Then we will return to the documentation
which has more computer generation. But
this next piece is going to be a few
thoughts that are selected from a larger
writing. Um just to
give a little bit of variety here, get
some feedback and um again also more to
be shared. So here we are
in 2022 paradol textbook figure 1.2
to summarizing the high road and the low
road.
So we want to have notation systems and
deployment methods for generative models
with expressive methods for and nested
addressable spaces of. So this next
series is going to be the spaces of our
capacity to do that task within
describe, design, render, simulate,
analyze, fit, assess performance of
described
models. Meaning there's a larger set of
models we can describe than we can
render. We can describe recipes we
cannot cook. And that's a good thing.
So zooming out there are these
concentric spaces of generative
models
which we have different capacities in a
given moment around for example let's do
in the
GNN
examples make another GNN file fast and
comprehensive
for a full selfdriving car. Ensure all
state faces and
ontology
ontological considerations
are accounted for with good GNN style.
So this is going to be an example of a
GNN file that we certainly cannot render
into a programming language in an
executable fashion yet, but with some
more constrain generation methods and
better type-checking in ways of looking
at which families of models and control
flows we can run. then it makes it just
an empirical fact that we can we can
describe systems that we can't even
visualize. Uh we could say it's a graph
with 100 trillion nodes and then there's
no computer that you have available that
can visualize that many. But that didn't
stop you from just writing the math on
the paper or just doing a visualization.
And then questions like the performance
of a given model for a given data set in
a setting is like seven horses ahead of
the cart from what is possible to
describe. So that's sort of like the
math to
application distance to travel which is
like consider this equation and this is
the attention factor and this one's the
regret factor and this one's the the
shame modulator and it's like you can
just write those math equations however
you want. No consideration to to too
much other than just ideally what each
of them mean.
But when it comes to saying well which
model would be a better fit of what
that's several steps ahead of actually
doing the testing and as long as that's
known then there's some interesting
cybernetic loops where you're like
describing multiple kinds of analytical
formulas with an insight which could be
right or wrong into which one of them
might be performant in a different way.
And sometimes your intuition might be
right and it's kind of like a
compressibility and there might be some
other uh irreducible jumps that just
like have to be computed on
through.
So when we're talking about performance
of a generative model like this one is
good at video games like this and that
that way or this one's driving or this
one's drone or recommending or resource
allocating whatever domain or function
you're making a generative model for
performance on one benchmark. So the
high jump approach or on a suite of
different measures kind of like a
decathlon.
It's a relational measurement,
assessment, or characterization that's
secondary to the primary phenotype or
embodiment. So map is not the territory.
Generative models are maps. So we're
talking about ctography, compositional
cognitive
cgraphy on territories which might be
themselves abstract or might be
embodied projects in and around the
active inference ecosystem. they have
performance and fitness wants and needs
and so on. So someone might think okay
well if this if I can design this kind
of algorithm with this kind of runtime
requirements with this performance by
this date with this amount of funding
then this is a viable method for us to
have a business. So all these different
kinds of performance or this should be
more efficient or more resilient against
this kind of intervention than this kind
of model. All those kinds of of
assessments that's all happening within
this larger space of generative models
which could be specified. So of course
like even the ones that we
describe are only a subset of what is
possible. So those generative models,
the larger spaces, the known unknowns
and the unknown
unknowns, they include the baroque,
absurd, tiny, useful, cute, funny, and
interesting. So here is
the GNN for the self-driving
car. So it's 566
lines. It could be made to be compliant
with different kinds of natural language
standards and these state spaces can be
type checked for their coherence and
their completeness. So, and then
especially with a sumo
type program like implementation of pure
active
ontology like definitions and other
kinds of sentence fragments. Then
there's all these different kinds of
static checking that could come into
play and resource estimation all the
early stages of the pipeline basically
up until but everything before 10 even
for this model that an LLM just blasted
out and that's not even with it having
an
MCP server.
So with the ability for all of these
methods within each module to be MCP
model context protocol methods then
compliant
generation of arbitrary generative
models can be dropped into the railroad
track which already is going to reliably
reach the triple play.
So we have the free energy principle
from the high road
and baze theorem statistics updating
learning on the bottom meeting at active
inference.
So that's why the low road is
implementation specific and the high
road is not because with the high road
we want to be able to use FE and related
methods
on biological organisms and arbitrary
levels of analysis or abstract systems.
So we want to be able to describe
systems we can't
build. Whereas the low road needs to be
able to build what it's describing. So
that would be that sort of bottom up
like a building must have
continuous connection even if it's
through like tension or something in
order to be x ft high. It just it's not
it's kind of a classic uh cranes and
skyhooks high road low road. So now
going a little bit further
here
consider that we have pair wise
information and distance measures today
in terms of software 1.0 in terms of
syntactic edit distance. So we can look
at two different programs or inputs
inputs as programs programs as inputs
and look at their syntactic differences.
More recently, we have gained
accessibility
of information and distance measures in
terms of software 2.0. So AI, neural
networks, machine learning as software
as per kind of the Andre Karpathy
post207
era, which is to say that we have these
compressive distances, semantic
distances, distances in so-called
semantic information geometry model
spaces. That's how RAG, it's how cursor
works, how LLMs work. Here's what's not
out there. Software 3.0 or it doesn't
even matter or need a number, but
cognitive computing distances. Now,
that requires a kind of perspectival
modeling which is least needed in
software 1.0 0 where there's discrete
numbers of changes to strings least to
not needed to have
multi-perspectivalism. Software 2.0 the
perspectivalism is very inshed with the
models geometry intrinsically. So we
could look at the embeddings of a given
input into multiple LLMs and consider
each of the LLM's embedding in terms of
compressive or semantic distances. So
it's it's not that it's impossible to
get
multi-perspectalism. It's just not it's
being implicitly welded together in the
trained state space of the LLM. What
about having a sort of first principles
active inference ontologically
specified pre always already
separation that gives true perspective
cognitive semantic information
differences differences that make
differences for sophisticated cognitive
agents. What's the accounting
system domain specific notation and then
general notation notation that lets us
cover diverse and unknown cognitive
phenomena addressing disperate systems
from a first principles perspective
which is the high road things we can
describe and imagine that we can't
necessarily
build and then by specification that's
larger than what we can build but where
where the crane and the skyhook
is when you have the active inference
model that is at the triple play point
where the math can be traced into the
math. The variables data supply chain
can be traced out to the next level and
then the ontologies and the assertions
that make up the rhetoric of the
scientific model can be also separately
broken out. And that's like pre- reverse
engineered to be massively composable in
this super useful
way. So what does it look like for those
cognitive
phenomena here in doc cognitive
phenomena. So here the read me in
cognitive phenomena is going to link to
each of these folders some of which
have files in them some don't. But just
to show let's do drag them all in
comprehensively go through this folder
of phenomena.
Ensure every subfolder has a technical
accurate readme and
a compliant GNN
file
showcasing the
phenomena. So here we have all these
different subfolders of cognitive
phenomena. This is the whole iguana.
This is the unifying approach to
different cognitive phenomena is
notationally. It doesn't mean that
there's functional unification per se.
It's not that there is a relevant edge.
First off, without a system of interest
or scope in mind, it it doesn't even
really make sense to say, well, is
attention related to language
processing? Like yeah in principle you
could design a system where there's any
kind of relationship within any kind of
anything because we're just imagining
different
recipes. Then if you
specify for a given system like for a
red harvester ant nestmate does this
relate to that? Well, then it starts to
become an inquiry that can actually be
pursued and whether or not they play
some sort of synergistic or trading off
role in a given situation as you've
defined it, as you've set up the
situation, etc., etc., etc.
At least there can be a unified notation
system so that within certain
spaces those notation systems could be
like fused, concatenated, tested for
difference and so
on. So COD 4.0 else on
it doing incredible work just iterating
comprehensively
through
and writing out uh the files as
requested and then again to the point of
like these are writing out recipes that
are fantastical but then there's a way
just like there's a way to build
different software into Linux there's a
to build approaches that bring you
closer and closer to the Grand Central
Station rendering
assembly. So let's let it go through
those examples read a little
more. So for this part was to say for
real
um first principles design of cognitive
computing with all of the relationality
and the multi-perspectivalism that
entails. We want to be able to do
semantic information distancing in
arbitrary multi-agent assemblies.
And I'm contending that some kind of
plain text format like GNN and
associated packaging and so on can help
support that coming to be the case even
today with the kinds of things we can
do. So in that light, the active
inference institute supports reliable
and effective applications of cognitive
computing and active inference across
domains. Different projects have
different domains and systems of
interest, but those are at the domain
level and they're connected through the
ontology, through the different tools.
There's all these different places where
somebody can focus on just a sub sub
domain or
anything. But how how how to gain access
to a common set of tools and and
and pipelines and methods? We can say
now make a GNN for this domain because
the notation and the rendering is being
strongly
typed. So we support that.
reliable effective application by
providing key services such as software.
So that includes inference libraries,
ones that we develop, ones that we just
rebroadcast the development of of
others, all kinds of examples of ways
that people are carrying out that
terminal inference. And then we host
things like the
ontology generalized notation notation
like what this stream is about cerebrum
the case specific rendering of different
generative models. There's sections in
the docs about cerebrum and also pushing
it further back
education because the metal rails of the
physical supply chain have their own
supply chain leading to the education
and the mind of the
engineer. So education and outreach and
awareness is also a part of it in terms
of how do we make something that is
lasting across generations and
translating into ways of working
together. Maintaining resources like
tech trees, professional training,
symposia, internships, inerson
educational programs and so on. These
are all different offerings and with
hopefully partner organizations we can
offer these better and different and
other and
more now just like dirt and asphalt
roads low roads so real generative
models that you actually build even if
it's just in drafting like a real recipe
you imagined let alone a real recipe
that you made let alone one that you
made like a business idea around. But
real low roads are built basically only
where and as and how needed less there
be a bridge to nowhere. You could. It's
like look being at the um Home Depot
supply store and looking at all this
material and thinking you could do this.
It's like yes, you could. And if it were
a quirky hobby or just a inexpressable
curiosity, it it it wouldn't even
necessarily be a bad thing. It just it
takes resources, not the least of which
time. So considered in that way there's
already many applications and
implementations of variational
approaches to
cybernetics all but active inference all
but the citation
network even narrowly considered. So
whether we look at our curated
implementations and the dozens of
explicit active inference
implementations that we've curated in
active blockfronts or whether we're just
thinking well if it's a variational
autoenccoder and it's using free energy
minimization to look at joint
distributions of perception cognition
action so on is that not basically doing
free energy minimization on the
particular partition and then we could
even take that further we could think
about this recent paper and recent guest
stream of Tuya isomer on this triple
equivalence and about the relationship
between neural
networks with their loss
function B graphs the kind that we're
working with more closely with the
factor graphs and B graphs and RX infer
and continuous turning machines how
those have a triple equivalence
so that that parenthetical was to Okay,
however, however deep you're going to
say active inference has already been
applied, whether you think uh take a
very narrow scalpel and say it's only
been applied in these opensource papers
that use exactly these criteria and
these software packages and these
calculations. Or if you zoom out and go
actually every calculation cannot but be
applying active inference. Wherever you
are in that sort of
frame, there are some low
roads and it is
all dots within
top-down notationally expressive
analytically described spaces of
generative models including
uh second layer notational systems which
we don't have or use here for
operational grammar for kind of control
flow. But just separating out this
generative
model probability
distribution description question from
the more operational side of of how it
is used. for example, the neural network
considered as a programming object and
math object and then how it's used with
what is sent to it when and all those
different kinds of things. So there are
some low roads maybe we think that the
low road should be there should be more
in this place or fewer in that place or
the ones that are dirt should stay dirt
and the ones that are this should be
that. We we may have some preferences or
some opinions on low road
distributions and it's a separate
related and separate topic to the
expressivity of the high road and the
generalizations which are not applying
to specific cases.
So consider this cognitive research tech
infrastructural situation analogous to
the metallurgy and alchemy of high
precision calipers which can be used to
describe and measure machine parts
during a material industrial revolution.
Hence our focus on accessibility, rigor,
applicability, education, sovereignty,
supply chains and security.
To recap that manual
section, common
dialectic rhetoric in active inference
related to the low road and the high
road. We want to be able to
understand where are we talking about
recipes that we can and can't do
different things with.
the the sort of in
that uh cooking lens. The best GNN
package would be for very large to all
known generative model types.
What is
express what is expressed
slashexpressable through natural
compositional language could be taken on
through at least s some steps like the
type checking the category theory um the
ontology even if it wasn't known how to
compute certain things still the
description could be analyzed on its own
terms
So in terms of applying active inference
and that being used in high reliability
settings, even if it's just high
reliability and important and meaningful
for you, we're talking about
performance, trade-offs, fitness,
phenotype, adaptability in specific
situations.
which is very far down the road from
imagining the recipe. So it's one thing
to be like I wonder how a nested
generative model for this and that would
work for this and if it could be used
for this and that important function and
then dot dot dot dot dot dot dot dot dot
dot dot here's my business plan that I
believe is going to work for how we're
going to do this and that. So that
there's a big space
between and that's where
the information supply chain for
generative models comes to be and
whether that's going to
be something that has to be blazed
through by
individuals and the sorts of failures
and trade-offs that would
incur andor which parts of that coast to
coast are
their well characterized methods for. So
in order for people who care about
performance to be able to even get to
the point of assessing it and not going
down this
lifelong learning to write generative
models specialty as it has largely been
at this point. In order for it to break
out of
that, having infrastructure that takes
on this
scope is going to be critical.
It will also provide some deeper
directions into the organization of
education and research and
professionalism through connection with
information
sciences cognitive computing.
So
meanwhile, let's update
GitHub.
Meanwhile, the LLM was going through the
cognitive phenomena folder and writing
GNN
files. So here's the learning and
adaptation
And this sets up a a a multi-channel
discussion. On one hand, there's the low
road discussion. Do we really think that
there should be this many state spaces?
No, I think there should be 25
dimensions or let's have this as a
variable and then do a sweep across how
many dimensions or what what are we
really talking about with the bstable
perception? Are we talking about the
ballerina spinning or are we talking
about the duck rabbit or that? So it
supports the technical discussion of
state spaces or for for a bio
regional setting. What variables are we
taking into account in this model? How?
And then there's there's this sort of
duel which is just separate from the
state space is like what are we doing
here? Should we be modeling
this? What are the feedbacks of us
modeling this in general and in specific
ways?
So just very interesting, useful
moments
that can have
some describable steps that take them
from basically
uh through the steps of cognitive
systems.
design. There's a few other new folders
in the
documentation.
[Music]
Um, some are related
to other
packages. There's also the tutorials.
Let's look at this in GitHub.
I'll look at these then maybe do one or
something random. So if anyone has a
comment or a question or wants to see
like a GNN model or some function then
just write it in the
chat some tutorials.
So first making a simple GNN
model basic
perception a simple model with one
hidden state and one observation. So
this is like the first model in step by
step hidden state with two
categories observation with two
categories connections
parameterization. Here's how you run
main to go on specific
steps to check at how it
works and then more future tutorials.
Um,
pipeline has some more information on
the pipeline itself.
pipeline
architecture has more on the control
flow, the purposes of the
different modules.
[Music]
Um
probably the main control flow could
could be
redesigned or
refactored but it works as it
is to uh call these functions which call
into
folders. So hopefully that gives some
touch
points. That's the forward
engineering. Let's let's separate out
one RX
infer
example scripts folder.
Let's
do hidden markoff
model and then if it is too challenging
maybe try the coin
toss.
Okay, that was just the cognitive
phenomena just showing you can make
subfolders with lists and so on and it
will
just rifle through them.
Okay, refactor this example unless
anyone makes a specific comment or
question. Start by just
running the script
plainly. Sometimes it it works in the
notebook format.
uh or other times it'll hit a Julia
error. Okay, there's the
error. I'm just this I'm just gonna tell
cursor this was from that
notebook so that it runs as a
script. Here is the error we get when we
run it.
Now, this could be done to first to to
to more cleanly do it. It probably could
be focus on having this only be one
script and f and get a single script
version like I did with a multi- aent or
in this case let's just go separate
it into as
many files in the folder as you
want.
Okay. So, it's going to start
to get
this hidden marov model RX
infer program running. And
meanwhile, this this could be done after
fully disassembled, but let's just try
it as
per. And
then I'll just drag in
the existing GNN files.
write and make to
this
folder a GNN file or the RX
infer hidden mark
of
model example all the
parameterization it would need as a GNN
And then where it's going to go is in
the app model block.
Instead of saying
B is this hard-coded matrix or A is an
identity matrix with a
33 those variables will
be extracted into this TOML or maybe
even we can go right to
GNN that's the reverse
engineering then the forward engineering
is in
render RX infer folder
say I'm trying to first off if this
could already be a GNN file we don't
even need to do the toml meet in the
middle
but if the parser can just directly use
this
information then it's good to
go
okay Now this config this GNN for the RX
infer POM
DP will not work in the multi- aent
trajectory avoidance example and vice
versa. So that is just to say there's a
lot more that we can diagnose and
refine
between
which GNN can be taken to what step in
what
uh language. But this
hmm like for example we
could let's just
say all changes to just ask mode. So it
just it's going to respond to not make
code edits. How are these
files similar and
different? Greetings Matias Conrath.
So imagine large libraries of GNN files,
some forensically reverse engineered
from examples and papers, others
generated from program
synthesis. And we could do different
kinds of probabilistic and deterministic
analyses on oh this this one differs all
but for this
or 80% of this had that but this one
didn't or something like
that. Key differences
similarities as mentioned earlier like
in the PMDP
A is the observation matrix. But in the
RX infer HMM, A is the state transition
matrix.
Okay, let's see how the refactoring is
going.
So here is that splitting from the
uh single craft
artifact, the local organic handmade
farmers market
style into the
IKEA
industrialized high reliability
information supply chain format.
Maybe it's hanging, but it is at least
getting broken up into separate
parts. Just letting it know that it's
hanging. Okay.
Triple
play. Okay. while it's fixing the
HMM. Various strategies and tactics may
be helpful when employing GNN
expressions in different settings and
using a spectrum of model
precisions, eg from informal
conversation to a beautiful presentation
to a fully
documented reproducible research
product. Model precision should be
balanced against the need for
comprehensiv
comprehensivity
comprehensibility could have been
comprehensivity too and ease of
communication. Broadly strategic
considerations for expressing GNN
include the overall approach to
communication such as the choice of
modality and level of technical rigor
applied for a given audience. Tactical
considerations for expressing GNN
include specific techniques for
enhancing clarity and understanding such
as using visual aids, examples, and
analogies.
AI
art using models for inference. Data on
inference models as
data markdown texts as data as GNN
files meeting the
visualization plain text markdown files.
meeting RX
infer with additional visualization and
methods. Kind of the magic of seeing GNN
work. Here we
go. So here on the right
side at least something is happening
Then
here it might be one moment too early to
do it, but to now add to the
pipeline add to the RX infer render
pipeline. If if we can reverse
engineer the HMM to to use the pure
markdown, we don't even need to render
it to this intermediate TOML.
But part of the reason why I wanted to
go to the TOML was I did that standalone
in another
repo just to get to a a controlled
input to show that there was a middle to
be met at.
Now that we know that there is a
middle to meet
at, we can basically just
go straight to
GNN and have example specific or
category specific
parsers, but that still needs to be
rendered in the GNN uh folder because
the other the side
information like the utility functions
that this HMM model
needs this wouldn't be in a GNN
file. So we need these kind
of kind of like a car
body and then the GNN parameterized
parts are like the
engine but there's a lot of functions in
code and so the way that was being done
in the multi- aent
setting was just by copying the folder
minus the config
So
if here it made the
HMM GNN in the GNN folder. So from the
point of view of
the HMM script folder, it still does not
have a GNN
file. But if this if it will succeed on
this
run, then we will have succeeded in
getting
to this face.
So this one we skipped going to a single
functional script went straight from the
notebook
uh extract to the modular software.
So one outcome of this step is
a
specific config
file.
Another emerging approach is directly to
target read write into GNN format
directly. Still needs the rendering
of
extra
parametric
information.
training program environment and flow
information that's not part of the
generative model. All
right, here we go. So, we got
the now it's
working for the hmm
inference. So, I'm going to delete the
original one or it could I'll move it to
archive or maybe it wants that one.
Okay, ceue up the next question.
Learn
again to confirm function
comprehensively output more in
standalone from standalone
file visualizations of free
energy values.
is so several prompts depending on the
example to disassemble
it. Meanwhile, let's try let's try
another approach which is not to
disassemble it. So this will be more
um first you have to get it running as a
script or we could develop a
plugin that goes directly to the
notebooks but it's so much nicer to have
it as these which can be concatenated
into a notebook too but at least you
know it's going to work. So while that
HMM is is
happening let's do another approach
which would
be for this
example write a GNN
file like
for
comprehensively setting all the needed
information for the bike
rental
demand
example and write
a Julia parser that confirms that
the GNN you wrote
will
perfectly align
with
the initial
example.
Okay, let's see how this
goes.
Remove any
unneeded files
too. Archive. Confirm that when running
the main
script, all data and visualizations are
saved to a timestamp folder.
Okay. So this is this would be an
example of if we can skip even further
steps by directly inserting in the GNN
repo the state space that needs to be
created for an RX infer example to
run.
Okay, let's see what
Julia. Okay.
So running comprehensive
HMM if anyone has any last uh ideas or
questions otherwise I'm going to take it
just a little bit further with this
HMM and uh bike
rental then maybe one triple play who's
on first and
seems
to be hanging
There it says and improve and
rerun
to
confirm. Here's the
validation parser
[Music]
test. This one also seems to be
hanging because
It's a small.
Okay. All right, let's just start
generating some of the baseball stuff.
Meanwhile,
[Music]
Um, next steps, seeing who watches and
comments and
emails and makes issues and
contributions on GitHub.
I'm going to keep working on the package
and the flow and the
methods
and putting
uh hopefully some useful and interesting
work
out but very much open to people's
support or or feedback on that.
That pretty
much is what I wanted to cover
today.
Okay. One
baseball related analysis and then that
will
be Golden
who's on
first. Oh, that was interesting. Only
one of us can be the first to do
something.
Wow. Only in the tone. Well,
there's only in the tone of the golden
spike. I'm going to be the first to say
that I'm not sure what the golden spike
is.
explore greatly within that topic in
allegorical
sequence
involving show not
tell approaches to category theory
and
recursive
selfdevelopment styled
exoterically as pun laden
quote who's on
burst style 1920s
illusion
environment make the dialogue
Totally
convey
in plain
quote basketball down the middle
style generalized notation
notation GNN
Interesting little error there,
huh? Can't be
deleted. Very
strange. Gone.
all the technical
elements, all the main SRC
elements, all the
documented
connections. Write this all
out vastly and
creatively. All
right. If anyone has any last question,
do write
it. Otherwise, look forward to
some collaboration on the
tooling and some fun interesting
discussions going a little more broadly.
How does this relate to to how we learn
and apply active inference? All these
topics
Yeah, it will be uh interesting to see
what prompt sequences, what measures of
information
are useful for these kind of
nested documentation and code
folders. How do you know when to
stop? All right, here it
is. Let's look at
it in GitHub.
Okay, I'll just read it.
I'll read it and then if anyone writes
any comment I might read that and then
that will be the
end. All right. The golden spike
dialogue. Who's on first base in
generalized notation notation scene.
1920s railroad depot. Two gentlemen in
bowler hats stand before a massive
scheduling board covered in cryptic
notations. One holds a golden spike. The
other clutches of stack of papers marked
GNN pipeline specification. Abbott.
Well, now Castello, we've got ourselves
quite the categorical conundrum here at
this generalized notation notation
depot. Say, Abbott, what's all this
gobbledegook about spikes and rails and
s_f031 type int? Looks like someone's
been playing alphabet soup with
mathematics. Ah, my dear fellow, you've
stumbled upon the very essence of our
enterprise. that there's a state space
variable, the foundation of our active
inference railroad system. Active what
now? I thought we were building a
railroad, not running a
gymnasium. No, no, no. Active inference,
my good man. It's about how minds make
models of the world. Think of it like
this. Every train car needs to know
where it's going, where it's been, and
what's around the bend. So, the train
cars are thinking precisely. Now, let me
show you our 14 stop construction
process. First, we start with step one.
The GNN parser. The what parser? The GNN
parser. It reads our standardized
notation files. Oh, I see. So, GNN
stands for good night
Nancy. Generalized notation notation.
That's what I said. Good night, Nancy
notation. No. No. GNN. It's our
textbased language for specifying these
thinking train systems. Well, why didn't
you say so? So, this Nancy notation
tells the trains how to think.
Let's move on. Step two is setup.
Absolutely critical, mind you. If setup
fails, the whole pipeline stops dead in
its tracks. Like a locomotive with a
busted boiler. Exactly. Then step three
runs our tests. Tests. What kinds of
tests do the train cars take written
exams? In a manner of speaking? Yes. We
validate their state spaces, check their
connections, ensure their probability
matrices are properly
stoastic. They're what? Astic matrices
stochastic. It means the probabilities
sum to one. Like making sure all the
passengers on a train car add up to the
total capacity. Ah, so if I got three
passengers in car A and two in car B, I
better have five total
passengers. Now you're getting it. Step
four is our type checker. It estimates
computational
resources. Type checker. Is that like
making sure the passenger manifest has
everyone's name spelled right? More like
making sure we have enough coal for the
engine and enough track for the journey.
It looks at your model and says, "This
will need X amount of memory, Y amount
of processing power." Smart. What's step
five? Export. We translate our GNN
models into different formats. JSON,
XML,
GraphML. Sounds like a whole lot of MLS
to me. What's GraphML stand for? Grumpy
Manatees
Language. Graph markup language.
Oh, that makes more sense. And step six,
visualization. We create beautiful
diagrams showing how all the state
factors connect to observation
modalities. Hold up there, fancy pants.
State factors. Observation what allies?
Think of it this way. State factors are
like different aspects of what's
happening inside the train car. Maybe
factor zero is how hungry the passengers
are and factor one is how tired they
are. Got it. An observation. What's it
modalities? Those are the different ways
you can sense what's going on. Maybe
modality zero is what you hear. Modality
one is what you
see. So the hungry, tired passengers in
the train car can be heard and seen.
Bingo. Now step seven gets really
interesting. That's our model context
protocol
integration. Model context what a call
protocol. It's like having a telegraph
system that lets different railroad
companies talk to each other using the
same language. Ah, so like Western Union
but for thinking trains. Exactly. Step 8
handles our ontology
processing or
whatology. Ontology. It's like having a
master dictionary that defines what
every term means in the active inference
world. So if I say belief and you say
belief, we both mean the same thing
precisely. Now, here's where it gets
really exciting. Step 9 renders our
models into executable code for
different simulation environments.
Executable code? Are we hanging
somebody? No. Executable means runnable.
We translate our GNN specifications into
Python code for PIMDP or Julia code for
RX
infer. Hold the phone there, Abbott.
PIMDP, RX infer. These sound like patent
medicines. PIMDP is Python for marov
decision processes discrete active
inference simulations. RX infers
reactive message passing in
Julia. So PMDP is like Python flavored
train scheduling in a sense. Yes. And RX
infer is like having a telegraph network
where messages bounce around updating
beliefs in real time. Telegraph network.
I like that. What's step 10? Execution.
We actually run the code we just
generated like firing up the locomotive.
Exactly. Step 11 is where we bring in
the big guns. LM integration. LM. Let me
guess. Large language
models. He knows that one. Very good. We
use AI to analyze and enhance our GNN
models. Provide natural language
explanation. So the thinking trains get
help from other thinking
trains. It's turtles all the way down,
my friend.
Step 12 is where things get
mathematically sublime. Disco pie
translation. Disco pie. Are we having a
dance party with dessert? Disco pie.
Distributional compositional Python.
It's category theory for string
diagrams. Category theory. What's that
got to do with railroad categories?
Fright, passenger, mail car. Now we're
getting to the philosophical heart of it
all. Category theory is mathematics that
studies how things compose together.
Like how you can connect train cars to
make longer
trains. So if I got a dining car and I
connect it to a sleeping car, I get a
dining sleeping
car. More like you get a composed system
where the properties of both cars work
together. The beauty is in the
connections, the morphisms between
objects. Morph
whatisms? The
arrows. the
relationships, how one thing transforms
into another. In our railroad, it's how
beliefs flow between different parts of
the system. Like how the conductor's
belief about the schedule flows to the
engineer's belief about when to blow the
whistle. Brilliant. You've grasped the
you've grasped the essence of
categorical composition. Step 13 uses
Jax for high performance
evaluation. Jax, is that short for
Jackson? just another executable. It's
Google's library for automatic
differentiation and just in time
compilation. Automatic different
what? It's like having a mathematical
microscope that can instantly tell you
how changing one little thing affects
everything else in your model. Like if I
change the coal input, it automatically
figures out how that changes the train
speed, passenger comfort, arrival
time. Exactly. And just in time
compilation means it optimizes the code
right when you need it. Like having a
master mechanic tune your engine on the
fly. Slick. Step 14. Site generation. We
generate beautiful documentation
websites showing off all our work. Like
a fancy brochure for the railroad
company. Precisely. Now let me show you
the recursive beauty of this whole
system. Recursive? That sounds like
something you need a doctor for. No. No.
Recursive means self-referential. The
system can model itself modeling things.
So the thinking train can think about
itself thinking about
thinking. Now you're getting into the
philosophical deep water. Each GNN model
is like a mirror that can reflect other
mirrors creating infinite depths of
self-awareness. Like when you stand
between two mirrors in a barber shop and
see yourself going on
forever. Beautiful analogy. And that's
where our state space blocks come in.
State space blocks are we're building
with Legos.
Now think of them as the blueprint
sections. Each block defines variables
with their dimensions and types like
s_f31 type int means state factor 0 is a
3x1 integer array. So it's like saying
car number one holds exactly three
passengers and we count them with whole
numbers precisely. And our connections
show how these blocks relate. We use
greater sign for directed relationships
hyphen for undirected ones. Like
engineer to conductor means the engineer
gives orders to the
conductor. Exactly. And passenger hyphen
passenger might mean passengers can talk
to each other both ways. # cerebrum.
This is starting to make sense. What
about those matrix things he mentions?
Ah, the ABC and D matrices. The heart of
active inference. ABC D. Sounds like
we're back in kindergarten. Matrix A is
your observation model. It tells you the
probability of seeing something given
what's actually happening. Like the
probability I'll hear the whistle given
that the train is approaching.
Perfect. Matrix B handles transitions.
How things change over time, possibly
based on actions. Like how pulling the
brake lever changes the train
speed. Right? Matrix C represents
preferences. what outcomes you'd prefer
to see, like preferring to arrive on
time rather than late. And matrix D
gives you your priors, what you believed
before you had any evidence, like
believing the train is probably on time
when you first arrive at the
station. You've mastered the
fundamentals. Now, here's where the
golden spike comes in. Finally, I was
wondering when we'd get to the spike. Is
it made of real gold?
The golden spike represents the moment
when all these separate components
connect into one unified system. When
PIMDP talks to RX infer when disco pi
diagrams execute as jacks code. When
loom analysis enhances human
understanding like when the eastern and
western railroads finally met in Utah.
Exactly that ceremonial spike joining
two great endeavors into one
transcontinental system. RGNN is the
golden spike of computational active
inference.
So this whole contraption, the 14 steps,
the thinking train cars, the matrix
algebbras, the category theories, it all
comes together to make one
big
what. A standardized way to describe,
validate, visualize, and simulate how
minds work. Whether it's a human brain,
an AI system, or a whole ecosystem of
interacting
agents. Agents, are we talking about
secret agents now?
Computational agents, anything that acts
based on beliefs and desires. Your train
conductor is an agent. He believes
certain things about the schedule and
desires to keep everything running
smoothly. And all these agents can be
described using this GNN notation.
from the simplest thermostat to the most
complex social system. Each one gets its
state states blocks, its connection
diagrams, its ABCD matrices and then
they can all talk to each other through
this model context protocol telegraph
system and be simulated in PIMDP or RX
infer visualized with pretty diagrams
analyzed by LLM translated to category
theory optimized with jacks and
documented on beautiful
websites will all be hornswaggled. So
this golden spike connects not just two
railroads but 14 different ways of
understanding thinking systems. 14
steps, infinite possibilities. From
parsing text files to generating
websites, from validating syntax to
executing simulations, it's all
connected by the golden thread of
standardized
notation. And anyone can learn this GNN
language. It's designed to be human
readable. Markdownbased files with clear
sections. Model name, state space,
block, connections, initial
parameterization. Sounds like a recipe
for building thinking trains. More like
a recipe for understanding how thinking
itself works. The recursive beauty is
that we use thinking systems to design
better thinking systems. Like using a
train to design better
trains. Exactly. And the category theory
ensures that when we compose these
models together, the whole system
remains mathematically consistent. like
making sure when you connect train cars,
they actually stay connected and don't
go flying off in different directions.
Beautiful. You've grasped the essence of
compositional modeling. Now, shall we
drive that golden spike? You
bet. But just one more question. When we
drive the spike, does it start the whole
14step pipeline? Indeed, it does. From
the first GNN parse to the final website
generation, it all begins with that
ceremonial connection. Then let's do
this thing for the transcontinental
railroad of computational
consciousness for active inference in
the standardization of thinking systems
everywhere. Three cheers for GNN. Hip
hip
hooray. Wait, Abbott. What happens after
we drive this
bike? Why then we start working on GNN
version 2.0? Of
course. Oh no, here we go again.
Right.
Another work
in exactly like William Blake
illuminated poem
status woven densely with
actual integrated William Blake.
quotes and
styles about
GNN
implicitly and
explicitly. Pretty funny baseball
ones. Delete the output
folder.
src Python 3 main.
Y regenerates the output folder.
And then in another
one
run pipeline
validation and
check comprehensively for full
functionality
of and
updated
streamlined documentation.
Still on step six with the
visualization those there's the
outputs
exports. So, like that self-driving car
that we made. That's probably why the
visualization is taking a long time
because now we have the self-driving car
GNN. So, I'll
pull. That's the trade-off with having a
bunch of the GNN files actively there,
but it'll be cool to
see. Archive has a bunch of
GNN. So, we can just run that one.
while it's writing the Blake
in. This is very
effective having the agent
run the
pipeline and then test it itself.
Now let's move to seven.
So like this is the
attempt to write the
TOML falling back on default
values trying to write the PIMDP
script. So, not a solved uh problem yet,
but okay. Let's see if this will work.
Otherwise, it I'll just end it here. But
I'll wait one minute, have a drink of
water, see if anyone writes a comment.
funny. Each of the three times it's
tried to write it, it's called it a
different file
name. Here's the visualization
of the self-driving car.
Yeah, it's
massive.
But so
cool. All the variables and ontology
terms for an LLM
generated
output. Four-fold vision of GNN. I hope
that one works.
Okay, looks like it is not to be like it
is to be unwritten.
So, thank you for watching. Hope people
can find out how to engage or support as
they see fit. contact blanket
activeinference.institute if you have
any questions or anything whenever that
may be. So till next time
[Music]